<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/" xmlns:s="http://jadedpixel.com/-/spec/shopify">
  <id>https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog.atom</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog.atom"/>
  <title>Social Pets - Pet Blog</title>
  <updated>2018-12-04T15:19:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Social Pets</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/winter-grooming-tips-for-your-dog</id>
    <published>2018-12-04T15:19:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2018-12-04T15:19:43-08:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/winter-grooming-tips-for-your-dog"/>
    <title>Winter Grooming Tips for Your Dog</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alan Tan</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>It’s winter in the Okanagan, which means the temperatures are starting to drop. Many owners are bringing their dogs into the grooming salon and asking for “one last shave down” before beginning to grow their pets coat out to keep them warm over winter. With the growth of a longer coat, it is important to remember that maintenance is still necessary to maintain skin and coat health in your dog. </p>
<p><br>Consider:<br><br><strong>Matting</strong> <br>Unfortunately, when a dog’s coat is left to grow long over winter, it usually comes at the cost of matting. But did you know that a dog with long, matted hair will be just as cold as if they were shaved? Mats hold moisture against the skin, which is not only cold but also creates an environment very susceptible to bacterial infections. Matting is also extremely uncomfortable for your dog as it causes them to be constantly itchy and irritated.<br><br><strong>Skin</strong><br>Regular baths and coat maintenance aid with the distribution of a dog’s natural oils. This helps to maintain the health of their skin and coat and prevent dry skin or dandruff. <br><br><strong>Nails</strong> <br>Nail clipping is included for any bath or haircut service provided by your groomer. In the summer, regular grooming appointments are enough to keep the nails clipped and in good condition. <br>In winter months, however, many dogs are unable to grind their nails down naturally. Without regular grooming appointments, the nails are left to grow to excessive lengths. It is not uncommon for nails to curl and grow into the dog’s pad, or for the nail to grow out to the side, twisting the dog’s toe to the side whenever they put weight on it (view image below). As you can imagine, both scenarios are painful for your dog. <br> <br><strong>Pads</strong><br>When dogs visit their groomers, they will always have their pads shaved. This is especially important in winter to prevent clumps of snow and road salt from becoming entangled in the hair between their pads, which can be painful and cause burning or irritation. <br><br>In conclusion, it is essential that regular grooming appointments are continued throughout the winter months. Many groomers recommend an appointment every 4 – 6 weeks, with regular brushing at home. With regular appointments, your groomer can maintain your dogs long winter coat, skin, nails, pads, and overall grooming health throughout the winter months.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/5-tips-for-successfully-adopting-a-rescue-dog</id>
    <published>2018-09-13T15:24:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2018-09-13T16:00:12-07:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/5-tips-for-successfully-adopting-a-rescue-dog"/>
    <title>5 Tips for Successfully Adopting a Rescue Dog</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alan Tan</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Are you ready to adopt?  This is the first and most important determinant in successfully adopting a rescue dog. The decision to adopt a dog should never be on impulse. Weeks or months of thought and discussion are vital to ensuring your entire family is prepared for the responsibility.</p><p><a class="read-more" href="https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/5-tips-for-successfully-adopting-a-rescue-dog">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong>Are you ready to adopt?</strong></p>
<p>This is the first and most important determinant in successfully adopting a rescue dog. The decision to adopt a dog should never be on impulse. Weeks or months of thought and discussion are vital to ensuring your entire family is prepared for the responsibility. For example, consider:</p>
<ul style="text-align: left;">
<li>Do you have the time and patience to properly integrate a rescue dog into your family and care for it for the rest of its life?</li>
<li>Are you financially able to handle all associated costs, such as vet bills and vaccinations, grooming, and food?</li>
<li>Do you have plans in place for if you travel? Will you be able to bring your dog with you if you suddenly need to move?</li>
</ul>
<p><b><br></b><strong>Consider personality</strong></p>
<p>Once you have decided you are ready to adopt a dog, it is time to consider which dog would be the best fit for your family. Although it may be tempting to take home the cutest looking puppy in the shelter, it is very important to find a dog with a personality compatible to your lifestyle. Do you work full time and then spend your free time watching Netflix? Consider a mellow, adult dog instead of a high-energy puppy. The shelter staff will be familiar with many of the dogs personalities, so consider asking them which dogs would suit your lifestyle best.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"> </p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Properly introduce your family members</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">This is especially important for families with young children. An addition of a new dog to the family will be exciting for your kids, and they will be tempted to play and cuddle the moment the dog is released from the crate. However, it is vital that all family members give the dog plenty of space and time to adjust to their new home. A scared dog is likely to find hugs or an invasion of personal space threatening and may become aggressive while trying to protect themselves. Allow the dog to cuddle or play on their terms, and make sure all initial interactions between your children and the dog are supervised.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"> </p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Properly introduce your other pets</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">It is important to make sure that your rescue dog will fit in well with any other animals you have at home. The rescue staff and volunteers should have an idea if the dog gets along with other dogs or cats. If it doesn’t, it may not be the dog for you. However, even if the dog is very friendly towards other animals, it is important to properly introduce them:</p>
<ul>
<li>Set up a room with food, water, toys, and bed or kennel for your new dog. When you bring him/her home, take them directly into the room and close the door.</li>
<li>When your new dog is comfortable in their room, bring in some of your other pet’s toys for him/her to smell. Also, take one of your new dogs toys out of the room for your other animals to smell.</li>
<li>After a day or so, lock your other animals in another room, and allow the rescue dog to explore the house. When they appear comfortable, introduce them to one on your current animals at a time. Ensure that all interactions are supervised until all of the animals are comfortable and watch for signs of stress.</li>
</ul>
<p style="text-align: left;"> </p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Be patient</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">There are many reasons a dog could be in a shelter. They may have been rescued from an abusive home, been found as a stray, or forfeited by a family who has no time for them. Regardless of the situation, the dog is likely to be scared and stressed. He/ she might take a while to warm up to you, and even older dogs might not have received proper training – which can often be frustrating. Just remember that with positive reinforcement, patience, and time, your new rescue dog will grow to be a great companion.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/5-signs-of-heat-stroke-in-dogs</id>
    <published>2018-08-30T12:40:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2018-08-30T12:46:47-07:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/5-signs-of-heat-stroke-in-dogs"/>
    <title>5 Signs of Heat Stroke in Dogs</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alan Tan</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Okanagan summers are HOT. With temperatures regularly exceeding 30°C, many of us are well aware of the risks of heat stroke in humans. But did you know that your dog is susceptible to heat stroke as well? Heat stroke in dogs has the potential to be fatal, so it is essential to be able to recognize the symptoms. </p><p><a class="read-more" href="https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/5-signs-of-heat-stroke-in-dogs">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>By Brittany Morgan</p>
<p>Okanagan summers are HOT. With temperatures regularly exceeding 30°C, many of us are well aware of the risks of heat stroke in humans. But did you know that your dog is susceptible to heat stroke as well? Heat stroke in dogs has the potential to be fatal, so it is essential to be able to recognize the symptoms. </p>
<p><strong>5 Signs of Heat Stroke in Dogs</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Excessive panting or drooling </li>
</ul>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Panting is a common way dogs cool themselves down. However, if they seem to be panting or drooling excessively very early in their walk, or they continue to pant for long after they have escaped the heat, it may indicate heat stroke.</p>
<ul>
<li>Vomiting or diarrhea </li>
</ul>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">There are various reasons a dog might experience vomiting or diarrhea. Heat stroke may be the cause if the dog has recently been exposed to high temperatures, such as a hot vehicle or a walk in the sun.</p>
<ul>
<li>Weakness or lethargy </li>
</ul>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">A lethargic dog will appear unusually calm and dazed. He/she may be sleeping more than usual, and not get excited when you grab their favorite toy or treat. They could also experience a loss of appetite.</p>
<ul>
<li>Tremors or seizures </li>
</ul>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Your dog may be shaking as if they are scared or cold. Seizures are also a sign of heat stroke, where your dog might fall on its side and become stiff, with their muscles twitching or jerking.</p>
<ul>
<li>Poor coordination</li>
</ul>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Your dog may become unable to walk or stand, appearing to be dizzy and falling over.</p>
<p><br><strong>What can you do if you think your dog has heat stroke?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Immediately seek a more cooling area with shade or air conditioning.Use cool (not ice cold) water to cool the dog down by dabbing it with a moist towel. Allow them to drink cool water if desired.Take your pet to your veterinarian as soon as possible. </li>
<li>How can you prevent your dog from getting heat stroke?</li>
<li>If left outside in warmer weather, ensure that your dog has access to water and shade.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>How To Lower The Risk Of Heat Stroke</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Never leave your dog in a warm vehicle. </li>
<li>If taking your dog for a walk, be aware of how your dog is acting. If he/she is walking slower than usual? Are they panting heavily after a short period of time? If so, it is likely too hot for your dog to be walking. Instead, try to walk your dog in the early morning or later in the evening when the temperature is cooler.</li>
<li>You could also exercise your dog by taking them for a swim in the lake or playing with a sprinkler in the backyard instead!</li>
<li>Recognize that senior dogs, puppies, obese dogs, or dogs with short snouts (Pugs, Bulldogs, Shih Tzu’s, etc.) are more prone to heat stroke than other breeds, and therefore require extra care in warm weather. </li>
</ul>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/what-is-the-best-food-for-puppies</id>
    <published>2018-05-26T00:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2018-06-08T00:29:57-07:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/what-is-the-best-food-for-puppies"/>
    <title>What Is The Best Food For Puppies?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alan Tan</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>What Is The Best Food For Puppies?  Just as a human baby or child has different nutritional needs from that of a grown adult, so do puppies likewise. Puppies tend to require a higher percentage of proteins and fats not only because their bodies are growing and developing but also because their smaller size requires burning more energy to maintain their body temperature.  </span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/what-is-the-best-food-for-puppies">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;">By Serene Chooi</p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<div style="text-align: left;">Just as a human baby or child has different nutritional needs from that of a grown adult, so do puppies likewise. Puppies tend to require a higher percentage of proteins and fats not only because their bodies are growing and developing but also because their smaller size requires burning more energy to maintain their body temperature.<br><br>Some larger breed puppies (e.g., Doberman Pinscher, Labrador Retriever) may need slightly less fat, protein and certain minerals like calcium and phosphorus to sustain healthy growth rates and avoid over-developmental orthopedic diseases.  <br><br>
</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">So, by the time a puppy is typically weaned off its mother's milk at about six weeks old, it is time to start introducing solid foods to its diet. </div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong></strong></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong><br>Types of Puppy Food </strong></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong></strong></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong><br>1. Dry* (Kibble) </strong></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">
<br>Dense in calories but lowest in moisture content (10%) so do provide fresh water to your puppy separately. Also, chewing kibble may not be as effective as raw bone in reducing tartar build-up in your puppy's teeth. The higher amount of carbohydrates (about 30-50%) found in dry puppy food is also, not nutritionally ideal. However, kibble is easiest on the wallet. </div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">* Freeze-dried and dehydrated foods (both &lt; 5% moisture content) are dry foods that are nutritionally superior to kibble but also more expensive. </div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong></strong></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong>2. Wet (Usually canned) </strong></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">
<br>Lower in calories compared to dry food but softer and certainly more palatable due to the flavored jelly or gravy holding the chunks of ingredients together. Wet puppy food is generally more nutritious than kibble due to the higher protein and fat content.  </div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">
<br>The major disadvantages are of course the higher price and higher moisture content (about 75-80%) which means having to feed your puppy a larger amount as compared to kibble.   </div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong></strong></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong><br>3. Semi-Moist </strong></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">This is more expensive than the above and is not recommended by veterinarians due to the higher salt and sugar content as well as artificial ingredients/flavorings. Even if your puppy is a fussy eater, this food is only meant to serve as an occasional treat.  </div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong></strong></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong><br>4. Raw </strong></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">Raw food includes meat with bone, organ meats, small amount of fruits and cooked vegetables and is deemed to be a 'traditional' balanced diet.  </div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">
<br>However, the major concern is food safety; improper raw food handling will result in foods carrying pathogens/parasites which can cause serious illnesses in puppies.  Some owners have resorted to sourcing raw meats directly from their butchers rather than purchasing commercial ones.  </div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">
<br>(Home prepared meals be it raw or cooked is challenging and requires knowledge to achieve the correct nutritional balance). </div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong></strong></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong><br>How Much to Feed My Puppy? </strong></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">
<br>The amount of food to feed your puppy depends on its size and weight and can be divided into three or four feedings a day, reducing to two as it approaches adulthood. </div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">
<br>A general rule of thumb is that you should be able to see your puppy's waist but not its ribs!  </div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong></strong></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong><br>In summary, we should:  </strong></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">
<ul>
<li>Buy the best that we can afford.  </li>
<li>Source for foods that are minimally processed and free of artificial ingredients. </li>
<li>Get puppy's food (not adult's) that comes with nutrients and in bite sizes that suit the puppy's breed.   </li>
</ul>
</div>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/which-dog-breed-is-right-for-you</id>
    <published>2018-05-25T23:29:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2018-06-08T00:37:51-07:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/which-dog-breed-is-right-for-you"/>
    <title>Which Dog Breed is Right for You?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alan Tan</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Which Dog Breed is Right for You?  How do you know which one will best fit for you and your family?  So many to choose from toy breeds to large breeds like the Great Dane.  Home and yard size, time to spend with them and how active a lifestyle you have are the biggest factors in choosing the right dog for you and your family.<p><a class="read-more" href="https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/which-dog-breed-is-right-for-you">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>By: Billie Losile</p>
<p>How do you know which one will best fit for you and your family?</p>
<div>So many to choose from toy breeds to large breeds like the Great Dane.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Home and yard size, time to spend with them and how active a lifestyle you have are the biggest factors in choosing the right dog for you and your family.</div>
<div></div>
<div><span><br><strong>Less Active Dog Breeds</strong><br><br></span></div>
<div><span></span></div>
<div></div>
<div>If you live in an apartment or condo, you would be best suited to a small breed dog like a Yorkshire Terrier or Shih Tzu. Most toy and small breed dogs need less exercise, so perfect for those who are lazy, not as active or cannot move around as well as they used to.<br><br>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Pugs would be a great fit for gamers out there. Pugs do not need a lot of attention and do not need a lot of exercise, do not get into a lot of mischief and would be content to sit by your side for hours while you played your favorite game.<br><br>
</div>
<div></div>
<div><strong>Average Active Dog Breeds</strong></div>
<div></div>
<div>
<br>A moderately active person, who walks a few times a week, loves to play and you love to comb and brush fur, I would suggest a Cocker Spaniel. Spaniels love attention and tend to get separation anxiety if away from their owners too much. Good choice for those that work from home, as well.</div>
<div></div>
<div>
<br>Another mid-sized dog that would be good for those at home a lot is a Shiba Inu. They do not get separation anxiety but do get destructive if left alone too much. If you have a well-fenced yard and only want one pet, a Shiba Inu might be for you.</div>
<div></div>
<div>If you are very active and want someone to go for runs or hike with you and have a large fenced yard, a German Shepherd or Golden Retriever might be a good fit for you.</div>
<div></div>
<div>
<br>German Shepherds also are great guard dogs and often used as police dogs. Golden Retrievers are more family dogs than guard dogs. They are even-tempered and responsible, so they would be good with kids.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Another great choice for a family would be a Boxer. The other big plus with a Boxer is less grooming so more time to play for those families always on the go.</div>
<div></div>
<div><span><br><strong>Very Active Dog Breeds</strong></span></div>
<div></div>
<div>
<br>If you have a large home and a large vehicle and yard, there are a lot of Giant dog breeds. Great Danes are super-sized but really just want to be lap dogs. They do not need a lot of exercise and have a coat that is easy to care for.</div>
<div></div>
<div>
<br>For a family wanting a dog to pull a toboggan or wagon and have a lot of love to give, a Saint Bernard might be a great fit. They need a lot of brushing and grooming but love to be a part of the family.</div>
<div></div>
<div>
<br>These are just a small handful of the vast number of dog breeds out there. When it comes time to choose the dog, please consider how much time you will have exercising and walking the dog, how much time you have for grooming and cleaning, how large your home is and who will be with the dog most of the time.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Go to dog parks, talk to the parents of the dogs there and ask questions. Check rescue societies and shelters and try to adopt from there.</div>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
