<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/" xmlns:s="http://jadedpixel.com/-/spec/shopify">
  <id>https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog.atom</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/tagged/dog-breeds.atom"/>
  <title>Social Pets - Pet Blog</title>
  <updated>2018-12-04T15:19:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Social Pets</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/which-dog-breed-is-right-for-you</id>
    <published>2018-05-25T23:29:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2018-06-08T00:37:51-07:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/which-dog-breed-is-right-for-you"/>
    <title>Which Dog Breed is Right for You?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alan Tan</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Which Dog Breed is Right for You?  How do you know which one will best fit for you and your family?  So many to choose from toy breeds to large breeds like the Great Dane.  Home and yard size, time to spend with them and how active a lifestyle you have are the biggest factors in choosing the right dog for you and your family.<p><a class="read-more" href="https://socialpets.ca/blogs/pet-blog/which-dog-breed-is-right-for-you">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>By: Billie Losile</p>
<p>How do you know which one will best fit for you and your family?</p>
<div>So many to choose from toy breeds to large breeds like the Great Dane.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Home and yard size, time to spend with them and how active a lifestyle you have are the biggest factors in choosing the right dog for you and your family.</div>
<div></div>
<div><span><br><strong>Less Active Dog Breeds</strong><br><br></span></div>
<div><span></span></div>
<div></div>
<div>If you live in an apartment or condo, you would be best suited to a small breed dog like a Yorkshire Terrier or Shih Tzu. Most toy and small breed dogs need less exercise, so perfect for those who are lazy, not as active or cannot move around as well as they used to.<br><br>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Pugs would be a great fit for gamers out there. Pugs do not need a lot of attention and do not need a lot of exercise, do not get into a lot of mischief and would be content to sit by your side for hours while you played your favorite game.<br><br>
</div>
<div></div>
<div><strong>Average Active Dog Breeds</strong></div>
<div></div>
<div>
<br>A moderately active person, who walks a few times a week, loves to play and you love to comb and brush fur, I would suggest a Cocker Spaniel. Spaniels love attention and tend to get separation anxiety if away from their owners too much. Good choice for those that work from home, as well.</div>
<div></div>
<div>
<br>Another mid-sized dog that would be good for those at home a lot is a Shiba Inu. They do not get separation anxiety but do get destructive if left alone too much. If you have a well-fenced yard and only want one pet, a Shiba Inu might be for you.</div>
<div></div>
<div>If you are very active and want someone to go for runs or hike with you and have a large fenced yard, a German Shepherd or Golden Retriever might be a good fit for you.</div>
<div></div>
<div>
<br>German Shepherds also are great guard dogs and often used as police dogs. Golden Retrievers are more family dogs than guard dogs. They are even-tempered and responsible, so they would be good with kids.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Another great choice for a family would be a Boxer. The other big plus with a Boxer is less grooming so more time to play for those families always on the go.</div>
<div></div>
<div><span><br><strong>Very Active Dog Breeds</strong></span></div>
<div></div>
<div>
<br>If you have a large home and a large vehicle and yard, there are a lot of Giant dog breeds. Great Danes are super-sized but really just want to be lap dogs. They do not need a lot of exercise and have a coat that is easy to care for.</div>
<div></div>
<div>
<br>For a family wanting a dog to pull a toboggan or wagon and have a lot of love to give, a Saint Bernard might be a great fit. They need a lot of brushing and grooming but love to be a part of the family.</div>
<div></div>
<div>
<br>These are just a small handful of the vast number of dog breeds out there. When it comes time to choose the dog, please consider how much time you will have exercising and walking the dog, how much time you have for grooming and cleaning, how large your home is and who will be with the dog most of the time.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Go to dog parks, talk to the parents of the dogs there and ask questions. Check rescue societies and shelters and try to adopt from there.</div>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
